<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
	<book category="1 Nephi">
		<chapter>
			<verse id="1">1 I, Nephi, having been born of goodly parents, therefore, I was taught somewhat in all the learning of my father; and having seen many afflictions in the course of my days--nevertheless, having been highly favored of the Lord in all my days; yea, having had a great knowledge of the goodness and the mysteries of God, therefore, I make a record of my proceedings in my days; yea, I make a record in the language of my father, which consists of the learning of the Jews and the language of the Egyptians.</verse>
			<verse id="2">2 And I know that the record which I make is true; and I make it with mine own hand; and I make it according to my knowledge.</verse>
			<verse id="3">3 ¶For it came to pass, in the commencement of the first year of the reign of Zedekiah, king of Judah (my father Lehi having dwelt at Jerusalem in all his days); and in that same year there came many prophets, prophesying unto the people that they must repent, or the great city Jerusalem must be destroyed.</verse>
			<verse id="4">4 Wherefore, it came to pass that my father Lehi, as he went forth, prayed unto the Lord, yea, even with all his heart, in behalf of his people.</verse>
			<verse id="5">5 ¶And it came to pass, as he prayed unto the Lord, there came a pillar of fire and dwelt upon a rock before him; and he saw and heard much; and because of the things which he saw and heard, he did quake and tremble exceedingly.</verse>
			<verse id="6">6 ¶And it came to pass that he returned to his own house at Jerusalem; and he cast himself upon his bed, being overcome with the Spirit and the things which he had seen;</verse>
			<verse id="7">7 And being thus overcome with the Spirit, he was carried away in a vision, even that he saw the heavens open, and he thought he saw God sitting upon his throne, surrounded with numberless concourses of angels in the attitude of singing and praising their God.</verse>
			<verse id="8">8 ¶And it came to pass that he saw one descending out of the midst of heaven, and he beheld that his luster was above that of the sun at noonday;</verse>
			<verse id="9">9 And he also saw twelve others following him, and their brightness did exceed that of the stars in the firmament; and they came down and went forth upon the face of the earth;</verse>
			<verse id="10">10 And the first came and stood before my father, and gave unto him a book, and bade him that he should read.</verse>
			<verse id="11">11 ¶And it came to pass that as he read, he was filled with the Spirit of the Lord, and he read, saying, Wo, wo unto Jerusalem! for I have seen thine abominations;</verse>
			<verse id="12">12 Yea, and many things did my father read concerning Jerusalem--that it should be destroyed, and the inhabitants thereof, many should perish by the sword, and many should be carried away captive into Babylon.</verse>
			<verse id="13">13 ¶And it came to pass that when my father had read and seen many great and marvelous things, he did exclaim many things unto the Lord; such as, Great and marvelous are thy works, O Lord God Almighty! Thy throne is high in the heavens, and thy power, and goodness, and mercy are over all the inhabitants of the earth; and because thou art merciful, thou wilt not suffer those who come unto thee that they shall perish!</verse>
			<verse id="14">14 And after this manner was the language of my father in the praising of his God; for his soul did rejoice, and his whole heart was filled, because of the things which he had seen; yea, which the Lord had shewn unto him.</verse>
			<verse id="15">15 And now I, Nephi, do not make a full account of the things which my father hath written, for he hath written many things which he saw in visions and in dreams;</verse>
			<verse id="16">16 And he also hath written many things which he prophesied and spake unto his children, of which I shall not make a full account; but I shall make an account of my proceedings in my days.</verse>
			<verse id="17">17 Behold I make an abridgment of the record of my father, upon plates which I have made with mine own hands; wherefore, after that I have abridged the record of my father, then will I make an account of mine own life.</verse>
			<verse id="18">18 ¶Therefore, I would that ye should know, that after the Lord had shewn so many marvelous things unto my father Lehi, yea, concerning the destruction of Jerusalem, behold he went forth among the people, and began to prophesy and to declare unto them concerning the things which he had both seen and heard.</verse>
			<verse id="19">19 ¶And it came to pass that the Jews did mock him because of the things which he testified of them; for he truly testified of their wickedness and their abominations;</verse>
			<verse id="20">20 And he testified that the things which he saw and heard, and also the things which he read in the book, manifested plainly of the coming of a Messiah, and also the redemption of the world.</verse>
			<verse id="21">21 ¶And when the Jews heard these things, they were angry with him; yea, even as with the prophets of old, whom they had cast out, and stoned, and slain;</verse>
			<verse id="22">22 And they also sought his life, that they might take it away.</verse>
			<verse id="23">23 But behold I, Nephi, will shew unto you that the tender mercies of the Lord are over all them whom he hath chosen, because of their faith, to make them mighty even unto the power of deliverance.</verse>
			<verse id="24">24 ¶For behold it came to pass that the Lord spake unto my father, yea, even in a dream, and saith unto him, Blessed art thou Lehi, because of the things which thou hast done;</verse>
			<verse id="25">25 And because thou hast been faithful and declared unto this people the things which I commanded thee, behold they seek to take away thy life.</verse>
			<verse id="26">26 ¶And it came to pass that the Lord commanded my father, even in a dream, that he should take his family and depart into the wilderness.</verse>
			<verse id="27">27 And it came to pass that he was obedient unto the word of the Lord, wherefore, he did as the Lord commanded him.</verse>
			<verse id="28">28 ¶And it came to pass that he departed into the wilderness.</verse>
			<verse id="29">29 And he left his house, and the land of his inheritance, and his gold, and his silver, and his precious things, and took nothing with him, save it were his family, and provisions, and tents, and he departed into the wilderness;</verse>
			<verse id="30">30 And he came down by the borders near the shores of the Red Sea;</verse>
			<verse id="31">31 And he traveled in the wilderness in the borders which were nearer the Red Sea;</verse>
			<verse id="32">32 And he did travel in the wilderness with his family which consisted of my mother Sariah, and my elder brothers, which were Laman, Lemuel, and Sam.</verse>
			<verse id="33">33 ¶And it came to pass that when he had traveled three days in the wilderness, he pitched his tent in a valley beside a river of water.</verse>
			<verse id="34">34 And it came to pass that he built an altar of stones, and he made an offering unto the Lord, and gave thanks unto the Lord our God.</verse>
			<verse id="35">35 And it came to pass that he called the name of the river Laman, and it emptied into the Red Sea; and the valley was in the borders near the mouth thereof.</verse>
			<verse id="36">36 ¶And when my father saw that the waters of the river emptied into the fountain of the Red Sea, he spake unto Laman, saying, O that thou mightest be like unto this river, continually running into the fountain of all righteousness.</verse>
			<verse id="37">37 And he also spake unto Lemuel, saying: O that thou mightest be like unto this valley, firm and steadfast, and immovable in keeping the commandments of the Lord.</verse>
			<verse id="38">38 Now this he spake because of the stiff-neckedness of Laman and Lemuel; for behold they did murmur in many things against their father, because that he was a visionary man, and that he had led them out of the land of Jerusalem, to leave the land of their inheritance, and their gold, and their silver, and their precious things, and to perish in the wilderness.</verse>
			<verse id="39">39 And this they said that he had done because of the foolish imaginations of his heart.</verse>
			<verse id="40">40 And thus Laman and Lemuel, being the eldest, did murmur against their father.</verse>
			<verse id="41">41 And they did murmur because they knew not the dealings of that God who had created them.</verse>
			<verse id="42">42 Neither did they believe that Jerusalem, that great city, could be destroyed according to the words of the prophets.</verse>
			<verse id="43">43 And they were like unto the Jews, which were at Jerusalem, which sought to take away the life of my father.</verse>
			<verse id="44">44 ¶And it came to pass that my father did speak unto them in the valley of Lemuel, with power, being filled with the Spirit, until their frames did shake before him.</verse>
			<verse id="45">45 And he did confound them, that they durst not utter against him; wherefore, they did do as he commanded them.</verse>
			<verse id="46">46 And my father dwelt in a tent.</verse>
			<verse id="47">47 ¶And it came to pass that I, Nephi, being exceeding young, nevertheless being large in stature, and also having great desires to know of the mysteries of God,</verse>
			<verse id="48">48 Wherefore, I cried unto the Lord; and behold he did visit me, and did soften my heart that I did believe all the words which had been spoken by my father; wherefore, I did not rebel against him like unto my brothers.</verse>
			<verse id="49">49 And I spake unto Sam, making known unto him the things which the Lord had manifested unto me by his Holy Spirit.</verse>
			<verse id="50">50 ¶And it came to pass that he believed in my words;</verse>
			<verse id="51">51 But behold Laman and Lemuel would not hearken unto my words:</verse>
			<verse id="52">52 And being grieved because of the hardness of their hearts, I cried unto the Lord for them.</verse>
			<verse id="53">53 ¶And it came to pass that the Lord spake unto me, saying, Blessed art thou Nephi, because of thy faith, for thou has sought me diligently, with lowliness of heart.</verse>
			<verse id="54">54 And inasmuch as ye shall keep my commandments, ye shall prosper, and shall be led to a land of promise; a land which I have prepared for you; yea, a land which is choice above all other lands.</verse>
			<verse id="55">55 And inasmuch as thy brethren shall rebel against thee, they shall be cut off from the presence of the Lord.</verse>
			<verse id="56">56 And inasmuch as thou shalt keep my commandments, thou shalt be made a ruler and a teacher over thy brethren.</verse>
			<verse id="57">57 For behold, in that day that they shall rebel against me, I will curse them even with a sore curse, and they shall have no power over thy seed, except they shall rebel against me also.</verse>
			<verse id="58">58 And if it so be that they rebel against me, they shall be a scourge unto thy seed, to stir them up in the ways of remembrance.</verse>
			<verse id="59">59 ¶And it came to pass that I, Nephi, returned from speaking with the Lord, to the tent of my father.</verse>
			<verse id="60">60 And it came to pass that he spake unto me, saying: Behold I have dreamed a dream, in the which the Lord hath commanded me that thou and thy brethren shall return to Jerusalem.</verse>
			<verse id="61">61 For behold, Laban hath the record of the Jews, and also a genealogy of my forefathers, and they are engraven upon plates of brass.</verse>
			<verse id="62">62 Wherefore, the Lord hath commanded me that thou and thy brothers should go unto the house of Laban, and seek the records, and bring them down hither into the wilderness.</verse>
			<verse id="63">63 And now, behold thy brothers murmur, saying it is a hard thing which I have required of them; but behold I have not required it of them; but it is a commandment of the Lord.</verse>
			<verse id="64">64 Therefore, go, my son, and thou shalt be favored of the Lord, because thou hast not murmured.</verse>
			<verse id="65">65 ¶And it came to pass that I, Nephi, said unto my father, I will go and do the things which the Lord hath commanded, for I know that the Lord giveth no commandments unto the children of men, save he shall prepare a way for them that they may accomplish the thing which he commandeth them.</verse>
			<verse id="66">66 ¶And it came to pass that when my father had heard these words, he was exceeding glad, for he knew that I had been blessed of the Lord.</verse>
			<verse id="67">67 And I, Nephi, and my brethren took our journey in the wilderness with our tents, to go up to the land of Jerusalem.</verse>
			<verse id="68">68 ¶And it came to pass that when we had come up to the land of Jerusalem, I and my brethren did consult one with another; and we cast lots which of us should go in unto the house of Laban.</verse>
			<verse id="69">69 And it came to pass that the lot fell upon Laman; and Laman went in unto the house of Laban, and he talked with him as he sat in his house.</verse>
			<verse id="70">70 And he desired of Laban the records which were engraven upon the plates of brass, which contained the genealogy of my father.</verse>
			<verse id="71">71 ¶And behold it came to pass that Laban was angry, and thrust him out from his presence; and he would not that he should have the records.</verse>
			<verse id="72">72 Wherefore, he said unto him, Behold thou art a robber, and I will slay thee.</verse>
			<verse id="73">73 But Laman fled out of his presence, and told the things which Laban had done, unto us.</verse>
			<verse id="74">74 And we began to be exceeding sorrowful, and my brethren were about to return unto my father in the wilderness.</verse>
			<verse id="75">75 But, behold, I said unto them, that as the Lord liveth, and as we live, we will not go down unto our father in the wilderness, until we have accomplished the thing which the Lord hath commanded us.</verse>
			<verse id="76">76 Wherefore, let us be faithful in keeping the commandments of the Lord;</verse>
			<verse id="77">77 Therefore, let us go down to the land of our father's inheritance, for behold he left gold and silver, and all manner of riches.</verse>
			<verse id="78">78 And all this he hath done, because of the commandments of the Lord; for he knowing that Jerusalem must be destroyed, because of the wickedness of the people.</verse>
			<verse id="79">79 ¶For behold, they have rejected the words of the prophets.</verse>
			<verse id="80">80 Wherefore, if my father should dwell in the land after that he hath been commanded to flee out of the land, behold he would also perish.</verse>
			<verse id="81">81 Wherefore, it must needs be that he flee out of the land.</verse>
			<verse id="82">82 And behold it is wisdom in God that we should obtain these records, that we might preserve unto our children the language of our fathers;</verse>
			<verse id="83">83 And also that we may preserve unto them the words which have been spoken by the mouth of all the holy prophets, which have been delivered unto them by the Spirit and power of God, since the world began, even down unto this present time.</verse>
			<verse id="84">84 ¶And it came to pass that after this manner of language did I persuade my brethren, that they might be faithful in keeping the commandments of God.</verse>
			<verse id="85">85 And it came to pass that we went down to the land of our inheritance, and we did gather together our gold, and our silver, and our precious things.</verse>
			<verse id="86">86 And after that we had gathered these things together, we went up again unto the house of Laban.</verse>
			<verse id="87">87 ¶And it came to pass that we went in unto Laban, and desired him that he would give unto us the records which were engraven upon the plates of brass, for which we would give unto him our gold, and our silver, and all our precious things.</verse>
			<verse id="88">88 ¶And it came to pass that when Laban saw our property, that it was exceeding great, he did lust after it, insomuch that he thrust us out, and sent his servants to slay us, that he might obtain our property.</verse>
			<verse id="89">89 And it came to pass that we did flee before the servants of Laban, and we were obliged to leave behind our property, and it fell into the hands of Laban.</verse>
			<verse id="90">90 ¶And it came to pass that we fled into the wilderness, and the servants of Laban did not overtake us, and we hid ourselves in the cavity of a rock.</verse>
			<verse id="91">91 And it came to pass that Laman was angry with me, and also with my father, and also was Lemuel; for he hearkened unto the words of Laman.</verse>
			<verse id="92">92 Wherefore, Laman and Lemuel did speak many hard words unto us, their younger brothers, and they did smite us even with a rod.</verse>
			<verse id="93">93 ¶And it came to pass as they smote us with a rod, behold an angel of the Lord came and stood before them, and he spake unto them, saying, Why do ye smite your younger brother with a rod?</verse>
			<verse id="94">94 Know ye not that the Lord hath chosen him to be a ruler over you, and this because of your iniquities?</verse>
			<verse id="95">95 Behold thou shalt go up to Jerusalem again, and the Lord will deliver Laban into your hands.</verse>
			<verse id="96">96 And after that the angel had spoken unto us, he departed.</verse>
			<verse id="97">97 And after that the angel had departed, Laman and Lemuel again began to murmur, saying, How is it possible that the Lord will deliver Laban into our hands?</verse>
			<verse id="98">98 Behold he is a mighty man, and he can command fifty, yea, even he can slay fifty; then why not us?</verse>
			<verse id="99">99 ¶And it came to pass that I spake unto my brethren, saying, Let us go up again unto Jerusalem, and let us be faithful in keeping the commandments of the Lord; for behold he is mightier than all the earth, then why not mightier than Laban and his fifty, yea, or even than his tens of thousands.</verse>
			<verse id="100">100 Therefore, let us go up; let us be strong like unto Moses; for he truly spake unto the waters of the Red Sea, and they divided hither and thither, and our fathers came through out of captivity on dry ground, and the armies of Pharaoh did follow and were drowned in the waters of the Red Sea.</verse>
			<verse id="101">101 Now behold ye know that this is true, and ye also know that an angel hath spoken unto you; wherefore, can ye doubt?</verse>
			<verse id="102">102 Let us go up; the Lord is able to deliver us, even as our fathers, and to destroy Laban even as the Egyptians.</verse>
			<verse id="103">103 ¶Now when I had spoken these words, they were yet wroth, and did still continue to murmur; nevertheless they did follow me up until we came without the walls of Jerusalem.</verse>
			<verse id="104">104 And it was by night: and I caused that they should hide themselves without the walls.</verse>
			<verse id="105">105 And after that they had hid themselves, I, Nephi, crept into the city, and went forth towards the house of Laban.</verse>
			<verse id="106">106 And I was led by the Spirit, not knowing beforehand the things which I should do.</verse>
			<verse id="107">107 Nevertheless I went forth, and as I came near unto the house of Laban, I beheld a man, and he had fallen to the earth before me, for he was drunken with wine.</verse>
			<verse id="108">108 And when I came to him I found that it was Laban.</verse>
			<verse id="109">109 And I beheld his sword, and I drew it forth from the sheath thereof, and the hilt thereof was of pure gold, and the workmanship thereof was exceeding fine: and I saw that the blade thereof was of the most precious steel.</verse>
			<verse id="110">110 ¶And it came to pass that I was constrained by the Spirit that I should kill Laban;</verse>
			<verse id="111">111 But I said in my heart, Never at any time have I shed the blood of man, and I shrunk and would that I might not slay him.</verse>
			<verse id="112">112 And the Spirit saith unto me again, Behold the Lord hath delivered him into thy hands; yea, and I also knew that he had sought to take away mine own life; yea, and he would not hearken unto the commandments of the Lord; and he also had taken away our property.</verse>
			<verse id="113">113 ¶And it came to pass that the Spirit said unto me again, Slay him, for the Lord hath delivered him into thy hands.</verse>
			<verse id="114">114 Behold the Lord slayeth the wicked to bring forth his righteous purposes.</verse>
			<verse id="115">115 It is better that one man should perish, than that a nation should dwindle and perish in unbelief.</verse>
			<verse id="116">116 ¶And now, when I, Nephi, had heard these words, I remembered the words of the Lord which he spake unto me in the wilderness, saying, That inasmuch as thy seed shall keep my commandments, they shall prosper in the land of promise.</verse>
			<verse id="117">117 Yea, and I also thought that they could not keep the commandments of the Lord according to the law of Moses, save they should have the law.</verse>
			<verse id="118">118 And I also knew that the law was engraven upon the plates of brass.</verse>
			<verse id="119">119 And again, I knew that the Lord had delivered Laban into my hands for this cause, that I might obtain the records according to his commandments.</verse>
			<verse id="120">120 Therefore, I did obey the voice of the Spirit, and took Laban by the hair of the head, and I smote off his head with his own sword.</verse>
			<verse id="121">121 ¶And after that I had smitten off his head with his own sword, I took the garments of Laban and put them upon mine own body; yea, even every whit; and I did gird on his armor about my loins.</verse>
			<verse id="122">122 And after that I had done this, I went forth unto the treasury of Laban.</verse>
			<verse id="123">123 And as I went forth towards the treasury of Laban, behold I saw the servant of Laban, which had the keys of the treasury.</verse>
			<verse id="124">124 And I commanded him in the voice of Laban, that he should go with me into the treasury; and he supposed me to be his master Laban, for he beheld the garments and also the sword girded about my loins.</verse>
			<verse id="125">125 And he spake unto me concerning the elders of the Jews, he knowing that his master Laban had been out by night among them.</verse>
			<verse id="126">126 And I spake unto him as if it had been Laban.</verse>
			<verse id="127">127 And I also spake unto him that I should carry the engravings which were upon the plates of brass, to my elder brethren, which were without the walls.</verse>
			<verse id="128">128 And I also bade him that he should follow me.</verse>
			<verse id="129">129 And he supposing that I spake of the brethren of the church, and that I was truly that Laban whom I had slain, wherefore, he did follow me.</verse>
			<verse id="130">130 And he spake unto me many times concerning the elders of the Jews, as I went forth unto my brethren, which were without the walls.</verse>
			<verse id="131">131 ¶And it came to pass that when Laman saw me, he was exceedingly frightened, and also Lemuel and Sam.</verse>
			<verse id="132">132 And they fled from before my presence; for they supposed it was Laban, and that he had slain me, and had sought to take away their lives also.</verse>
			<verse id="133">133 ¶And it came to pass that I called after them, and they did hear me; wherefore, they did cease to flee from my presence.</verse>
			<verse id="134">134 And it came to pass that when the servant of Laban beheld my brethren, he began to tremble, and was about to flee from before me, and return to the city of Jerusalem.</verse>
			<verse id="135">135 ¶And now I, Nephi, being a man large in stature, and also having received much strength of the Lord, therefore, I did seize upon the servant of Laban, and held him that he should not flee.</verse>
			<verse id="136">136 ¶And it came to pass that I spake with him, that if he would hearken unto my words, as the Lord liveth, and as I live, even so that if he would hearken unto our words, we would spare his life.</verse>
			<verse id="137">137 And I spake unto him, even with an oath, that he need not fear; that he should be a free man like unto us, if he would go down in the wilderness with us.</verse>
			<verse id="138">138 And I also spake unto him, saying, Surely the Lord hath commanded us to do this thing, and shall we not be diligent in keeping the commandments of the Lord?</verse>
			<verse id="139">139 Therefore, if thou wilt go down into the wilderness to my father, thou shalt have place with us.</verse>
			<verse id="140">140 ¶And it came to pass that Zoram did take courage at the words which I spake.</verse>
			<verse id="141">141 Now Zoram was the name of the servant; and he promised that he would go down into the wilderness unto our father.</verse>
			<verse id="142">142 Yea, and he also made an oath unto us, that he would tarry with us from that time forth.</verse>
			<verse id="143">143 Now we were desirous that he should tarry with us for this cause, that the Jews might not know concerning our flight into the wilderness, lest they should pursue us and destroy us.</verse>
			<verse id="144">144 ¶And it came to pass that when Zoram had made an oath unto us, our fears did cease concerning him.</verse>
			<verse id="145">145 And it came to pass that we took the plates of brass and the servant of Laban, and departed into the wilderness, and journeyed unto the tent of our father.</verse>
			<verse id="146">146 ¶And it came to pass that after we had come down into the wilderness unto our father, behold he was filled with joy, and also my mother Sariah was exceeding glad, for she truly had mourned because of us; for she had supposed that we had perished in the wilderness;</verse>
			<verse id="147">147 And she also had complained against my father, telling him that he was a visionary man; saying, Behold thou hast led us forth from the land of our inheritance, and my sons are no more, and we perish in the wilderness.</verse>
			<verse id="148">148 And after this manner of language had my mother complained against my father.</verse>
			<verse id="149">149 ¶And it had come to pass that my father spake unto her, saying, I know that I am a visionary man; for if I had not seen the things of God in a vision, I should not have known the goodness of God, but had tarried at Jerusalem, and had perished with my brethren.</verse>
			<verse id="150">150 But behold I have obtained a land of promise, in the which things I do rejoice;</verse>
			<verse id="151">151 Yea, and I know that the Lord will deliver my sons out of the hands of Laban, and bring them down again unto us in the wilderness.</verse>
			<verse id="152">152 And after this manner of language did my father Lehi comfort my mother Sariah concerning us, while we journeyed in the wilderness up to the land of Jerusalem, to obtain the record of the Jews.</verse>
			<verse id="153">153 ¶And when we had returned to the tent of my father, behold their joy was full, and my mother was comforted;</verse>
			<verse id="154">154 And she spake, saying, Now I know of a surety that the Lord hath commanded my husband to flee into the wilderness;</verse>
			<verse id="155">155 Yea, and I also know of a surety that the Lord hath protected my sons, and delivered them out of the hands of Laban, and gave them power whereby they could accomplish the thing which the Lord hath commanded them.</verse>
			<verse id="156">156 And after this manner of language did she speak.</verse>
			<verse id="157">157 ¶And it came to pass that they did rejoice exceedingly, and did offer sacrifice and burnt offerings unto the Lord; and they gave thanks unto the God of Israel.</verse>
			<verse id="158">158 And after that they had given thanks unto the God of Israel, my father Lehi took the records which were engraven upon the plates of brass, and he did search them from the beginning.</verse>
			<verse id="159">159 And he beheld that they did contain the five books of Moses, which gave an account of the creation of the world;</verse>
			<verse id="160">160 And also of Adam and Eve, which were our first parents;</verse>
			<verse id="161">161 And also a record of the Jews from the beginning, even down to the commencement of the reign of Zedekiah, king of Judah;</verse>
			<verse id="162">162 And also the prophecies of the holy prophets, from the beginning, even down to the commencement of the reign of Zedekiah;</verse>
			<verse id="163">163 And also many prophecies which have been spoken by the mouth of Jeremiah.</verse>
			<verse id="164">164 ¶And it came to pass that my father Lehi also found upon the plates of brass a genealogy of his fathers;</verse>
			<verse id="165">165 Wherefore, he knew that he was a descendant of Joseph; yea, even that Joseph which was the son of Jacob, which was sold into Egypt, and which was preserved by the hand of the Lord, that he might preserve his father Jacob and all his household from perishing with famine.</verse>
			<verse id="166">166 And they were also led out of captivity and out of the land of Egypt, by that same God who had preserved them.</verse>
			<verse id="167">167 And thus my father Lehi did discover the genealogy of his fathers.</verse>
			<verse id="168">168 And Laban also was a descendant of Joseph, wherefore, he and his fathers had kept the records.</verse>
			<verse id="169">169 ¶And now when my father saw all these things he was filled with the Spirit, and began to prophesy concerning his seed; that these plates of brass should go forth unto all nations, kindreds, tongues and people, which were of his seed.</verse>
			<verse id="170">170 Wherefore, he said that these plates of brass should never perish, neither should they be dimmed any more by time.</verse>
			<verse id="171">171 And he prophesied many things concerning his seed.</verse>
			<verse id="172">172 ¶And it came to pass that thus far I and my father had kept the commandments wherewith the Lord had commanded us.</verse>
			<verse id="173">173 And we had obtained the record which the Lord had commanded us, and searched them and found that they were desirable; yea, even of great worth unto us, insomuch that we could preserve the commandments of the Lord unto our children.</verse>
			<verse id="174">174 Wherefore, it was wisdom in the Lord that we should carry them with us as we journeyed in the wilderness towards the land of promise.</verse>

		</chapter>
		<chapter>
			<verse id="1">1 ¶And now I, Nephi, do not give the genealogy of my fathers in this part of my record; neither at any time shall I give it after upon these plates which I am writing; for it is given in the record which has been kept by my father; wherefore, I do not write it in this work.</verse>
			<verse id="2">2 For it sufficeth me to say that we are a descendant of Joseph.</verse>
			<verse id="3">3 And it mattereth not to me that I am particular to give a full account of all the things of my father, for they cannot be written upon these plates, for I desire the room that I may write of the things of God.</verse>
			<verse id="4">4 For the fullness of mine intent is that I may persuade men to come unto the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, and be saved.</verse>
			<verse id="5">5 Wherefore, the things which are pleasing unto the world, I do not write, but the things which are pleasing unto God and unto them which are not of the world.</verse>
			<verse id="6">6 Wherefore, I shall give commandment unto my seed, that they shall not occupy these plates with things which are not of worth unto the children of men.</verse>
			<verse id="7">7 And now I would that ye might know, that after my father Lehi had made an end of prophesying concerning his seed, it came to pass that the Lord spake unto him again, saying, that it was not meet for him, Lehi, that he should take his family into the wilderness alone; but that his sons should take daughters to wife, that they might raise up seed unto the Lord in the land of promise.</verse>
			<verse id="8">8 ¶And it came to pass that the Lord commanded him that I, Nephi, and my brethren, should again return unto the land of Jerusalem, and bring down Ishmael and his family into the wilderness.</verse>
			<verse id="9">9 ¶And it came to pass that I, Nephi, did again, with my brethren, go forth into the wilderness to go up to Jerusalem.</verse>
			<verse id="10">10 And it came to pass that we went up unto the house of Ishmael, and we did gain favor in the sight of Ishmael, insomuch that we did speak unto him the words of the Lord.</verse>
			<verse id="11">11 ¶And it came to pass that the Lord did soften the heart of Ishmael and also his household, insomuch that they took their journey with us down into the wilderness to the tent of our father.</verse>
			<verse id="12">12 And it came to pass that as we journeyed in the wilderness, behold Laman and Lemuel, and two of the daughters of Ishmael, and the two sons of Ishmael, and their families, did rebel against us; yea, against I, Nephi, and Sam, and their father Ishmael, and his wife, and his three other daughters.</verse>
			<verse id="13">13 ¶And it came to pass in the which rebellion they were desirous to return unto the land of Jerusalem.</verse>
			<verse id="14">14 And now I, Nephi, being grieved for the hardness of their hearts, therefore, I spake unto them, saying, yea, even unto Laman and unto Lemuel, Behold thou art mine elder brethren; and how is it that ye are so hard in your hearts, and so blind in your minds, that ye have need that I, your younger brother, should speak unto you, yea, and set an example for you?</verse>
			<verse id="15">15 How is it that ye have not hearkened unto the word of the Lord?</verse>
			<verse id="16">16 How is it that ye have forgotten that ye have seen an angel of the Lord?</verse>
			<verse id="17">17 Yea, and how is it that ye have forgotten how great things the Lord hath done for us in delivering us out of the hands of Laban, and also that we should obtain the record?</verse>
			<verse id="18">18 Yea, and how is it that ye have forgotten that the Lord is able to do all things according to his will, for the children of men, if it so be that they exercise faith in him; wherefore, let us be faithful in him.</verse>
			<verse id="19">19 And if it so be that we are faithful in him, we shall obtain the land of promise; and ye shall know at some future period that the word of the Lord shall be fulfilled concerning the destruction of Jerusalem;</verse>
			<verse id="20">20 For all things which the Lord hath spoken concerning the destruction of Jerusalem must be fulfilled.</verse>
			<verse id="21">21 For behold, the Spirit of the Lord ceaseth soon to strive with them;</verse>
			<verse id="22">22 For behold they have rejected the prophets and Jeremiah have they cast into prison.</verse>
			<verse id="23">23 And they have sought to take away the life of my father, insomuch that they have driven him out of the land.</verse>
			<verse id="24">24 ¶Now behold, I say unto you, that if ye will return unto Jerusalem ye shall also perish with them.</verse>
			<verse id="25">25 And now, if ye have choice, go up to the land, and remember the words which I speak unto you, that if ye go ye will also perish; for thus the Spirit of the Lord constraineth me that I should speak.</verse>
			<verse id="26">26 ¶And it came to pass that when I, Nephi, had spoken these words unto my brethren they were angry with me.</verse>
			<verse id="27">27 And it came to pass that they did lay their hands upon me--for behold, they were exceeding wroth--and they did bind me with cords, for they sought to take away my life, that they might leave me in the wilderness to be devoured by wild beasts.</verse>
			<verse id="28">28 ¶But it came to pass that I prayed unto the Lord, saying, O Lord, according to my faith which is in me, wilt thou deliver me from the hands of my brethren;</verse>
			<verse id="29">29 Yea, even give me strength that I may burst these bands with which I am bound.</verse>
			<verse id="30">30 ¶And it came to pass that when I had said these words, behold, the bands were loosed from off my hands and feet, and I stood before my brethren, and I spake unto them again.</verse>
			<verse id="31">31 And it came to pass that they were angry with me again, and sought to lay hands upon me;</verse>
			<verse id="32">32 But behold, one of the daughters of Ishmael, yea, and also her mother, and one of the sons of Ishmael, did plead with my brethren, insomuch that they did soften their hearts; and they did cease striving to take away my life.</verse>
			<verse id="33">33 ¶And it came to pass that they were sorrowful, because of their wickedness, insomuch that they did bow down before me, and did plead with me, that I would forgive them of the thing that they had done against me.</verse>
			<verse id="34">34 ¶And it came to pass that I did frankly forgive them all that they had done, and I did exhort them that they would pray unto the Lord their God for forgiveness.</verse>
			<verse id="35">35 And it came to pass that they did so.</verse>
			<verse id="36">36 And after that they had done praying unto the Lord we did again travel on our journey toward the tent of our father.</verse>
			<verse id="37">37 ¶And it came to pass that we did come down unto the tent of our father.</verse>
			<verse id="38">38 And after that I and my brethren, and all the house of Ishmael, had come down unto the tent of my father, they did give thanks unto the Lord their God;</verse>
			<verse id="39">39 And they did offer sacrifice and offer burnt offerings unto him.</verse>
			<verse id="40">40 ¶And it came to pass that we had gathered together all manner of seeds of every kind; both of grain of every kind, and also of the seeds of fruits of every kind.</verse>
			<verse id="41">41 And it came to pass that while my father tarried in the wilderness he spake unto us, saying, Behold, I have dreamed a dream; or in other words, I have seen a vision.</verse>
			<verse id="42">42 And behold, because of the thing which I have seen, I have reason to rejoice in the Lord because of Nephi, and also of Sam; for I have reason to suppose that they, and also many of their seed, will be saved.</verse>
			<verse id="43">43 But behold, Laman and Lemuel, I fear exceedingly because of you; for behold, methought I saw in my dream a dark and dreary wilderness.</verse>
			<verse id="44">44 ¶And it came to pass that I saw a man, and he was dressed in a white robe; and he came and stood before me.</verse>
			<verse id="45">45 And it came to pass that he spake unto me, and bade me follow him.</verse>
			<verse id="46">46 And it came to pass that as I followed him, and after that I had followed him, I beheld myself that I was in a dark and dreary waste.</verse>
			<verse id="47">47 And after that I had traveled for the space of many hours in darkness I began to pray unto the Lord, that he would have mercy on me according to the multitude of his tender mercies.</verse>
			<verse id="48">48 ¶And it came to pass that after I had prayed unto the Lord, I beheld a large and spacious field.</verse>
			<verse id="49">49 And it came to pass that I beheld a tree, whose fruit was desirable to make one happy.</verse>
			<verse id="50">50 ¶And it came to pass that I did go forth and partake of the fruit thereof; and I beheld that it was most sweet above all that I ever had before tasted.</verse>
			<verse id="51">51 Yea, and I beheld that the fruit thereof was white, to exceed all the whiteness that I had ever seen.</verse>
			<verse id="52">52 And as I partook of the fruit thereof, it filled my soul with exceeding great joy;</verse>
			<verse id="53">53 Wherefore, I began to be desirous that my family should partake of it also; for I knew that it was desirable above all other fruit.</verse>
			<verse id="54">54 And as I cast my eyes round about, that perhaps I might discover my family also, I beheld a river of water; and it ran along, and it was near the tree of which I was partaking the fruit.</verse>
			<verse id="55">55 And I looked to behold from whence it came; and I saw the head thereof a little way off;</verse>
			<verse id="56">56 And at the head thereof I beheld your mother Sariah, and Sam, and Nephi; and they stood as if they knew not whither they should go.</verse>
			<verse id="57">57 ¶And it came to pass that I beckoned unto them; and I also did say unto them with a loud voice that they should come unto me and partake of the fruit, which was desirable above all other fruit.</verse>
			<verse id="58">58 ¶And it came to pass that they did come unto me, and partake of the fruit also.</verse>
			<verse id="59">59 And it came to pass that I was desirous that Laman and Lemuel should come and partake of the fruit also;</verse>
			<verse id="60">60 Wherefore, I cast mine eyes towards the head of the river, that perhaps I might see them.</verse>
			<verse id="61">61 ¶And it came to pass that I saw them, but they would not come unto me, and partake of the fruit.</verse>
			<verse id="62">62 And I beheld a rod of iron; and it extended along the bank of the river, and led to the tree by which I stood.</verse>
			<verse id="63">63 And I also beheld a straight and narrow path, which came along by the rod of iron, even to the tree by which I stood;</verse>
			<verse id="64">64 And it also led by the head of the fountain unto a large and spacious field, as if it had been a world;</verse>
			<verse id="65">65 And I saw numberless concourses of people, many of whom were pressing forward, that they might obtain the path which led unto the tree by which I stood.</verse>
			<verse id="66">66 ¶And it came to pass that they did come forth and commenced in the path which led to the tree.</verse>
			<verse id="67">67 And it came to pass that there arose a mist of darkness; yea, even an exceeding great mist of darkness, insomuch that they which had commenced in the path did lose their way, that they wandered off and were lost.</verse>
			<verse id="68">68 ¶And it came to pass that I beheld others pressing forward, and they came forth and caught hold of the end of the rod of iron;</verse>
			<verse id="69">69 And they did press forward through the mists of darkness, clinging to the rod of iron, even until they did come forth and partake of the fruit of the tree.</verse>
			<verse id="70">70 And after that they had partaken of the fruit of the tree they did cast their eyes about as if they were ashamed.</verse>
			<verse id="71">71 And I also cast my eyes round about, and beheld on the other side of the river of water a great and spacious building;</verse>
			<verse id="72">72 And it stood as it were in the air, high above the earth;</verse>
			<verse id="73">73 And it was filled with people, both old and young, both male and female;</verse>
			<verse id="74">74 And their manner of dress was exceeding fine;</verse>
			<verse id="75">75 And they were in the attitude of mocking and pointing their fingers towards those which had come at, and were partaking of the fruit.</verse>
			<verse id="76">76 And after that they had tasted of the fruit they were ashamed, because of those that were scoffing at them; and they fell away into forbidden paths and were lost.</verse>
			<verse id="77">77 ¶And now I, Nephi, do not speak all the words of my father.</verse>
			<verse id="78">78 But, to be short in writing, behold, he saw other multitudes pressing forward; and they came and caught hold of the end of the rod of iron; and they did press their way forward, continually holding fast to the rod of iron, until they came forth and fell down and partook of the fruit of the tree.</verse>
			<verse id="79">79 And he also saw other multitudes feeling their way towards that great and spacious building.</verse>
			<verse id="80">80 ¶And it came to pass that many were drowned in the depths of the fountain;</verse>
			<verse id="81">81 And many were lost from his view, wandering in strange roads.</verse>
			<verse id="82">82 And great was the multitude that did enter into that strange building.</verse>
			<verse id="83">83 And after that they did enter into that building they did point the finger of scorn at me, and those that were partaking of the fruit also; but we heeded them not.</verse>
			<verse id="84">84 These are the words of my father: For as many as heeded them, had fallen away.</verse>
			<verse id="85">85 And Laman and Lemuel partook not of the fruit, saith my father.</verse>
			<verse id="86">86 ¶And it came to pass that after my father had spoken all the words of his dream or vision, which were many, he said unto us, because of these things which he saw in a vision, he exceedingly feared for Laman and Lemuel;</verse>
			<verse id="87">87 Yea, he feared lest they should be cast off from the presence of the Lord;</verse>
			<verse id="88">88 And he did exhort them then with all the feeling of a tender parent, that they would hearken to his words, in that, perhaps the Lord would be merciful to them, and not cast them off;</verse>
			<verse id="89">89 Yea, my father did preach unto them.</verse>
			<verse id="90">90 ¶And after that he had preached unto them, and also prophesied unto them of many things, he bade them to keep the commandments of the Lord;</verse>
			<verse id="91">91 And he did cease speaking unto them.</verse>
			<verse id="92">92 And all these things did my father see, and hear, and speak, as he dwelt in a tent, in the valley of Lemuel; and also a great many more things, which cannot be written upon these plates.</verse>
			<verse id="93">93 And now, as I have spoken concerning these plates, behold, they are not the plates upon which I make a full account of the history of my people;</verse>
			<verse id="94">94 For the plates upon which I make a full account of my people, I have given the name of Nephi;</verse>
			<verse id="95">95 Wherefore, they are called the plates of Nephi, after mine own name; and these plates also are called the plates of Nephi.</verse>
			<verse id="96">96 ¶Nevertheless, I have received a commandment of the Lord that I should make these plates for the special purpose that there should be an account engraven of the ministry of my people.</verse>
			<verse id="97">97 Upon the other plates should be engraven an account of the reign of the kings, and the wars and contentions of my people;</verse>
			<verse id="98">98 Wherefore, these plates are for the more part of the ministry; and the other plates are for the more part of the reign of the kings, and the wars and contentions of my people.</verse>
			<verse id="99">99 Wherefore, the Lord hath commanded me to make these plates for a wise purpose in him; which purpose I know not.</verse>
			<verse id="100">100 But the Lord knoweth all things from the beginning;</verse>
			<verse id="101">101 Wherefore, he prepareth a way to accomplish all his works among the children of men; for behold he hath all power unto the fulfilling of all his words.</verse>
			<verse id="102">102 And thus it is. Amen.</verse>
		</chapter>
	</book>
</root>
